What if I told you there was a buried
study conducted in the 1960s that only
50 years later was the data recovered
and released to the public? And what if
I told you that study showed seed oils
are harming our cardiovascular health?
Well, that's not what I'm claiming, but
it is claimed by many, including some
doctors like Dr. Paul Mason, a sports
medicine physician that makes the rounds
against seed oils. Those are vegetable
oils extracted from plants like soybean
oil, canola oil, safflower oil, and so
on. So, we're going to hear what Dr.
Mason outlines in relation to this
hidden study recently released to the
public by a separate group of
researchers. And then we're going to
separate fact from fiction, if any
fiction exists, of course, because it
could very well be that this study has
simply been buried to stop the truth
from getting out. Let's hear about this
study. You may have also heard of the
Sydney Diet Heart Study, a good quality
randomized control trial examining in
men who'd had heart attacks the effect
of replacing saturated fat with
polyunsaturated fat. And the result on
whether or not this diet actually
reduced the risk of death was actually
destined to never be published. That's
right. It was only a stroke of luck that
a researcher uncovered the original
study data in a basement and was able to
decode it and publish it some 40 years
after the study was concluded. And so in
2013, the results of the Sydney Diet
Heart Study were finally published in
the British Medical Journal. The
conclusion, reducing saturated fat in
the diet and increasing polyunsaturated
fats increased the risk of death by 62%.
Wow, that's astonishing. I mean, if we
step back and think about that, that
flies in the face of so many other
studies. This study indicates reducing
saturated fat and increasing omega6
polyunsaturated fats, those are the seed
oils, leads to an over 60% increase in
death. Holy cow. Saturated fat and all,
that's a bombshell. And then the fact
that this study was buried and only
recently, well over 10 years ago now,
published really has one wondering if
these scientists were deceiving the
public with their malevolent.
What's this? Could it be? How is this
possible? Dare I admit it? The original
study published by the original authors
has spawned out of the annals of
history. But hold on, I thought this
study was buried and only recently
recovered. Am I dreaming or was that
whole narrative a bunch of croc? Surely
not.
Well, regardless of if this study was
buried or not, the fact remains the seed
oil group experienced a massive increase
in death. Let's look at the data from
the original study and then let's bring
in some additional damning data from the
new analysis. Here we're seeing the
survival over 5 years consuming either a
seed oil diet or a saturated fat favored
diet, the dotted line and the solid line
respectively. If the lines go down, that
means that there's less survival, a bad
thing. So, Dr. Mason is absolutely right
when saying that there is an increase in
death from the seed oil diet. In fact,
the bad news doesn't end there because
in a more recent analysis that Dr. Mason
brings up, the researchers were able to
tease out not only all cause mortality
data, but also cardiovascular specific
disease. The blue line is the seed oil
group. This time, the higher the line
goes, the greater the cardiovascular
disease incidence. That's a 70%
increased risk in cardiovascular
disease, by the way. So, some pretty
scary stuff, but there have been some
critiques of these two studies, the
suddenly published original study and
the reanalysis, and Dr. Mason, to his
credit, addresses some of them. This is
probably one of the most important bits
of research you've never heard about.
and truth be told, one that you almost
didn't find out about. Now, of course,
evidence like this which undermines the
orthodox view on dietary fat is not
going to be unchallenged, and indeed, it
did face a barrage of criticism, most of
it deceptive and irrelevant. The one
argument that most often gets repeated
is that the 62% increased risk of death
was due to an increase in trans fat
consumption. Specifically, it is claimed
that the margarine consumed in the
intervention group was high in trans
fat. And for all intents and purposes,
this argument is the only justification
these saturated fatfearing zealots have
for ignoring the harms of
polyunsaturated seed oils. This
argument, however, is flawed. It comes
down to the difference between hard and
soft margarines. Hard margarine did back
then contain trans fats. However, the
margarine used in the study was Miracle
Brand, a soft margarine and clearly
advertised as such. And soft margarines
contained very little, if any, trans
fats. And the consumption of biscuits,
cakes, pastries, and puddings, all of
which were often made with trans fat
containing hard margarine, was expressly
discouraged in the intervention group.
Furthermore, safflower oil, which also
contains little if any trans fat, was
used in the intervention group, further
displacing other sources of trans fats.
The upshot of all this is that the trans
fat intake of the intervention group
almost certainly reduced which leaves us
with the uncomfortable truth that the
increase in polyunsaturated oils in the
diet as recommended by our current
dietary guidelines increased the chance
of dying by 62%.
All shown by a good quality long-term
randomized control trial. Okay, some
pretty harsh words there from Dr. Mason.
And might he have a point? In fact, he
does. One of the main critiques of this
Sydney heart trial is the fact that
people that switched to margarine, which
was this seed oil, omega6 fat focused,
would also be consuming large amounts of
trans fats as trans fats were not known
to be deletterious to health. Dr. Mason
then points out that this critique is
deceptive and that's because only hard
margarine had trans fats in them and the
study participants consumed more miracle
brand margarine which did not contain
trans fats. Obviously on the face of it
that's a good argument and there's even
compelling argument in that train of
thought from the reanalysis researchers.
They mentioned that the intervention
group, the seed oil group, was
instructed to avoid common margarine and
were instructed to, as Dr. Mason
mentioned, consume miracle brand
margarine, which contained only
safflower oil and very little trans
fats. So, if anything, the control group
was consuming more saturated fat and
trans fats from common margarates.
Like I said, on the face of it, that's a
good argument. But if we peek under the
hood of the argument for even a
millisecond, we notice some major
issues. One, although we were just told
that Miracle Brand had no trans fat,
that's just flat incorrect. A chairman
of nutrition research at Sydney
University along with other researchers
mentioned that Miracle Brand very likely
had trans fats at the time with an
estimated 15% of the margarine being
trans fat. In addition, in the original
study, the authors mentioned that the
intervention group, the seed oil group,
were told to reduce their saturated fat
to less than 10% of calories and to
replace it with polyunsaturated fats at
a minimum of 15% of calories. To be
fair, it should also be mentioned that
the control group was also allowed to
use margarine instead of butter.
However, we know for a fact that the
intervention group consumed more
polyunsaturated fats and a chunk of that
came from margarine containing trans
fats. Not to mention that they were not
discouraged from using other margarine
like the control group. So, while the
reanalysis researchers and Dr. Mason
might speculate that trans fats were
lower in the seed oil group, that seems
unlikely and has been pointed out by
other researchers.
But we've been focused on the trans fat
critique. Believe it or not, there are
other critiques that aren't mentioned.
So, let's get into those. And if you're
interested in this full analysis, I have
more that I mention in the extended
version of this video that you're
watching. That video analysis, plus all
the perks of the Physionic Insider
membership, including a private podcast,
exclusive video library, research
reviews, live sessions with me, and
more, can be found in the description
box with a Physionic Insider membership.
would love to discuss this study in more
depth with you. Check it out. So far, it
really seems like there's a lot of
narrative and not much truth being told.
In fact, I'll give you another prime
example later without even introducing
any new data. But for now, let's discuss
a bit more on the critiques. So, we've
discussed how trans fats were highly
likely in margarine because it was used
ubiquitously at the time and margarine
had trans fats. They don't anymore. FYI,
however, you might have also noticed
that I mentioned that the researchers
allowed the control group to consume
margarine when they felt like it. What
do you think that does to the study
design if you allow both groups to do
similar things?
It muddies the results. So statements
like all shown by a good quality
long-term randomized control trial are
hard to listen to when the researchers
themselves acknowledge the difference
between the diets wasn't as big as
they'd hoped. Not to mention the
researchers themselves did further
analyses on the data that they had to
determine what tracks strongly with the
results and they determined that diet
was not associated with increased
mortality and did not have predictive
power.
What did have predictive power was the
use of digitalis a medication used for
to treat heart disease. The presence of
chest pains, history of diabetes,
divorce, and a few other measures of
heart rhythm by electroc cardiogram. All
of those culminate to bad baseline heart
health predicting mortality. The reason
diet wasn't linked was for multiple
reasons. One, the study had poor
statistical power, meaning that it
didn't include enough data because it
didn't have enough participants to
detect an effect. This was likely
married to the fact that the diets had
significant variability and weren't
different enough from one another. It's
also possible that the researchers
overcorrected statistically speaking,
masking what effect might be there from
the diet. The point being that even if
we argue that the diet was the main
factor that led to these negative
results of omega sixs, there's several
points that indicate the lack of
reliability in these results. Of course,
we could turn to this newer analysis,
but even that analysis has received fair
critiques, like the fact that the
researchers didn't address all potential
confounding variables, factors that may
have actually caused the effect aside
from the diet. For example, they
adjusted for several factors, but did
not account for all the predictive
factors that we just described earlier.
In addition, the original study
researchers pointed out that physical
activity was especially predictive of
positive outcomes, i.e. reduced
mortality. Again, this was not adjusted
for in the newer analysis. There are
some other critiques that get into study
methodology and statistics, but the
bottom line is it wasn't based on strong
foundation of data and the reanalysis
was missing some pieces. To be fair,
some of this is understandable simply
because, well, the sample size is too
small. But it again speaks to the notion
that this study is flawed in many ways
that aren't being brought up. As a final
point, as promised, listen to this. You
may have also heard of the Sydney Diet
Heart Study, a good quality randomized
control trial examining in men who'd had
heart attacks the effect of replacing
saturated fat with polyunsaturated fat.
And the result on whether or not this
diet actually reduced the risk of death
was actually destined to never be
published. That's right. It was only a
stroke of luck that a researcher
uncovered the original study data in a
basement and was able to decode it and
publish it some 40 years after the study
was concluded. So, as we went over, we
somehow found the study that was never
published in its published form earlier
by a stroke of good fortune since we
just looked for it. But I like the
wording here, especially a stroke of
luck that the researchers uncovered the
original study data in a basement.
Really gives you those uh we tried to
bury this. But you meddling kids had to
get into our affairs and ruin things.
Like I promised, no new data. We can
just open the same studies that Dr.
Mason cites. And right here we can
clearly see that the reanalysis team
just asked for the data from one of the
original authors, this guy, and they
received it. Doesn't exactly make for a
compelling conspiracy, but maybe if they
added in there that they had to capture
him as he made a rapid escape out the
back door using his walker with the data
under his arm. Maybe, I don't know,
throw in a gunfight and some torture.
Where's the data, old man? Something
along those lines. Who knows? Maybe they
did have to get the data from a
basement. But the researchers certainly
don't give the impression that this was
hidden. So, the takeaway here is that
the Sydney Heart trial was an ambitious
endeavor. And although it was a
randomized control trial, it was
confounded by multiple factors pertinent
to the times. The data was not hidden.
It was published decades ago and further
analyzed again by another team. Finally,
this study is not a basis to accept or
refute seed oils, omega-6 fats. For
that, we need to look at more data,
which I'll be releasing a 200 study
analysis here in a few days to answer if
seed oils should be avoided. It's a far
bigger rabbit hole than I anticipated.
Until then, check out this other seed
oil conspiracy study by the ever
malicious Anel Keys. Or is it another
nothing burger with saturated fat? Of
course.